好的，欢迎来到功能架构。
Okay, welcome to functional architecture.
我是布赖恩·朗斯多夫，我会是你的老师。
I'm Brian Lonsdorf, I'll be your teacher.
我们今天将学习架构和函数式编程。
And we're gonna learn about architecture and functional programming today.
所以，教学架构存在这个问题。
So, there's this issue with teaching architecture.
它总是发生在你尝试教授建筑和
Its always happens where you try to teach architecture and
它会有所有这些好处。
it's gonna have all these benefits.
但是当你教它的时候，你实际上不能在课堂上展示它们，因为你
But you can't actually show them in the class when you're teaching it because you
希望示例足够简单，可以在一天内完成理解。
want the examples to be simple enough to consume and understand in a day.
而建筑真的只有在你达到这种突破点时才会得到回报。
And architecture really only pays off once you hit this kind of breaking point.
有足够的复杂性，你的应用程序变得足够大。
There's enough complexity and your app gets big enough.
所以我们将尝试平衡这条线 看看我们如何
So we're gonna try to balance that line and look at how we can
一旦应用程序变得足够大，应用这种架构就可以获得好处。
apply this architecture to get benefits once the app gets kind of big enough.
那么，我们的目标是什么？
So, what is our goal?
为什么，我们为什么要这样做？
Why, why are we doing this?
我们希望我们的应用程序更加模块化还是
Do we want our apps to be more modular or
我们是否需要它们更具可扩展性、性能或可维护性？
the, do we need them to be more extensible or performance or maintainable?
每个应用程序都有一组不同类型的您想要追求的值。
Each app has a different kind of set of values that you wanna go after.
所以对于我们今天的指南针，我认为总的来说，我们可以建立
And so for our compass today and in general I think, we can establish
您开始的功能架构的一个很好的目标。
a good goal for functional architecture that you start with.
由于您有不同的要求，您可以专注于不同的目标。
And as you have different requirements, you can focus on different goals.
那么这个目标是什么？
So what is that goal?
我们可以在这里做什么？
What can we do here?
让我们退后一步，看看这段代码。
Let's just take a step back and look at this code.
这是一个漫长的过程，你不必阅读它。
It's a long procedure, you don't have to read it.
但是当我们做建筑时，我们真正在做的是我们只是一种群体
But what we're really doing when we do architecture is we just kind of group
事物。
things.
然后我们给他们一个名字。
And then we give them a name.
因此，我们将这些命名过程分组。
So we have these named procedures that we've grouped.
然后我们把那些有名字的程序分成更多的组，
And then we group those procedures with names into more groups,
我们称之为模块、模块或类。
and we call this modulars, modules or classes.
然后那些得到名字。
And then those get names.
然后我们有数据类型。
And then we have datatypes.
我们将数据分组到这些小包中。
And we group data into these little bundles.
然后我们给出这些名字。
And then we give those names.
我们在名字之上有名字，这个巨大的名字云。
We have names on tops of names on tops of names, this giant cloud of names.
感谢 Joe Nelson 提供幻灯片。
Thank you to Joe Nelson for the slide.
就是想叫出来
Just wanna call that out.
所以，领域驱动设计是一本好书。
So, Domain Driven Design is a great book.
它真的，真的告诉你如何通过隐喻和使用这些名称和
It really, really tells you how coding by metaphor and using these names and
真正进入使用无处不在的领域，
really getting into the zone of of using ubiquitous,
无处不在的语言来模拟现实世界。
ubiquitous language to model the real world.
真的，真的很努力，直到你把它提炼成完美的比喻。
And really, really hammering on that until you distill it into the perfect metaphors.
我们这里的隐喻有点问题。
And we kind of have a problem with metaphors here.
您必须了解域和上下文。
One you have to know about the domain and context.
你不能只是跳进一个应用程序。
You can't just jump into an app.
您必须了解代码本身中没有的所有内容才能理解
You have to know everything about what's not in the code itself to understand
代码。
the code.
然后我们最终得到像处理器和转换器这样的东西。
And then we end up with like these things like processor and converter.
那不是真实的世界，
That's not real world,
如果您曾经编写过处理器类，请举手。
like raise your hand if you've ever written a processor class.
所以你，你最终得到了这些计算机东西的混合隐喻，
So you're, you end up with these mixed metaphors of computer stuff and
现实世界的东西和事物随着时间的推移而发展并变得模糊
real world stuff and things evolve over time and blur and
你最终会得到这个功能的大杂烩。
you end up with this hodgepodge of functionality.
有各种按名称分组，但是
There's all kind of grouped by name, but
功能可以以不同的方式分组。
the functionality may be grouped in different ways.
所以，马上，如果我们要捕获程序
So, right off the bat, if we're gonna be capturing procedures for
重用，我们只依赖于一个名字，我们不知道我们能用它做什么，
reuse and we're just depending on a name, we don't know what we can do with that,
真的，没有实际的构图规则。
really, there's no actual rules of composition.
如果我们打算在对它进行分组和命名后重新组合它，
If we're planning on recomposing this after grouping it and naming it,
我们不知道我们是否可以多次运行它。
we don't know if we can run it more than once.
我们可以以不同的顺序运行它吗？
Can we run it in different orders?
它是否改变了我们程序的其他部分？
is it changing other parts of our program?
它是如何交互的？
How does it interact?
所以我们实际定义的这些东西并不是真的
So these things that we are actually defining don't really
成为我们程序中的知识。
become knowledge in our program.
所以我们想在这里关注这些属性，对吗？
So we want to focus on these properties here, right?
每当我们开发一个存储过程时，
Whenever we develop a stored procedure,
我们想要围绕组合的属性。
we want to have properties around composition.
毕竟，我们正在重用这些东西。
After all, we're reusing these things.
我们将在不同的情况下编写它们。
We're gonna be composing them in different situations.
这些法律保护我们免于仅仅混淆名称。
And these laws are what protect us from just the confusion of the name alone.
所以我们的第一个目标是找到定义好的函数
So our first goal is to find functions with defined
合约，主要是那些数学属性。
contracts,mainly those mathematical properties.
所以我们要看看这个类，那是用户和
So we are gonna look at this class ,that's user and
我们这里有一个全名。你是完美的，对吧？
we have a full name here.,and yhis is perfect, right?
我们有一个全名功能，工作得很好。
We have a full name function, works just fine.
我们有 Bobby Fischer，他出来了。
We have Bobby Fischer, comes right out.
所以，我们在这里要做的另一件事是尝试分解并概括它。
So, another thing we're gonna do here is try to break this down and generalize it.
让我们看看这个过程是如何工作的。
Let's see how that process works.
所以我们有一个用户类型和一个全名函数。
So we have a user type and a full name function.
在这里，我们有效地加入了与班级相同的事情。
And here we're joining the same thing as the class effectively.
它以相同的结果结束。
And it ends up with the same result.
但是如果我们进一步概括它，我的意思是，我们只是传递名字和
But what if we generalize it further, I mean, we're just passing first name and
姓。
last name.
为什么我们不创建一个带有空格函数的连接？
Why don't we create a join with spaces function?
我们不必称呼它的名字或姓氏，并且
We don't have to call it first or last name, and
最终是完全相同的功能，但它更加通用和可重用。
ends up being the same exact function, but it's much more generic and reusable.
看，我们有属性，它是关联的。
And look, we have properties, it's associative.
事实证明，我们可以以任何嵌套顺序调用 jonWithSpace。
Turns out, we can call jonWithSpace in any nested order.
只要这一切都叫
As long as it's all called,
我们如何关联括号并不重要，这就是关联的含义。
it doesn't matter how we associate the parentheses, that's what associated means.
这是这个通用函数的可组合契约。
And that's a composable contract for this generic function.
我要再研究一下泛型函数。
I'm gonna hammer on generic functions for a little while longer.
在这里使用 joinWithSpaces，我们可以更进一步，称之为可连接。
Here with joinWithSpaces, we could take it a step further and call it joinable.
我们将采用任何可连接并在其上调用 join ，然后我们将传入数组。
We'll take any joinable and called join on it and then we'll pass in the array.
从字面上看，joinWithSpaces 无能为力
And literally, there's nothing joinWithSpaces can do
除了 call join 之外，因为它对它的数据类型一无所知。
other than call join, because it knows nothing about its data type.
所以通过概括，我们正在减少可能性，更简单的实现，
So by generalizing, we're making less possibility, simpler implementations,
更多的重用，它变成了一个更通用的泛化函数。
more reuse, and it becomes a more generic generalized function.
我们实际上收集了我们恢复封装的内容。
And we actually gather what we recover encapsulation.
对象通过信息隐藏给我们封装，但是
Objects give us encapsulation through information hiding, but
这实际上是信息隐藏。
this effectively is information hiding.
如果我们只知道我们可以在我们的对象上调用 join，
If we only know we can call join on our objects,
我们对此一无所知，我们正在隐藏信息。
we know nothing else about it, we're hiding information.
我们可以把它带到逻辑上，只定义这个身份函数。
And we can take that to its logical end and just define this identity function.
而这个恒等函数，它对这个a一无所知，
And this identity function, it knows nothing of this a,
它只是需要一个 a 并返回一个 a。
it's just gonna take an a and return an a.
如果它调用任何东西或对它做任何事情，我的意思是，
And if it called anything on it or did anything to it, I mean,
它会破坏那种拿走任何东西并将其归还的合同。
it would break that contract of taking anything at all and returning it back.
因此，通过对此一无所知并将其概括为逻辑结果，
So by not knowing anything about this and generalizing it to its logical end,
尽我们所能，我们实际上是在做信息隐藏和
as much as we can make it general, we're actually doing information hiding and
保护我们自己免受整个应用程序的涟漪变化。
protecting ourselves from rippling changes across our application.